It sure used to be a lot easier to be from Iceland,
من المؤكد انه كان فيما مضى من الاسهل كون المرء من آيسلندا
because until a couple of years ago,
لانه قبل عامين
people knew hardly anything about us,
ما كان أحدٌ يعرف الكثير عن آيسلندا
and I could basically come out here
وكان من الممكن الصعود على هذه المنصة والتحدث
and say only good things about us.
فحسب بالامور الجيدة عن بلدي آيسلندا
But in the last couple of years
ولكن منذ عامين
we've become infamous for a couple of things.
اصبحنا مشهورين بأمرين
First, of course, the economic meltdown.
الاولى .. هو الانهيار الاقتصادي
It actually got so bad
والذي تطور من سيء إلى أسوء
that somebody put our country up for sale on eBay.
لدرجة ان احدهم قام بوضع دولتنا على لائحة المشتريات في موقع " إي باي "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ninety-nine pence was the starting price
وكان سعر البدء في الشراء هو 99 سنتاً فحسب
and no reserve.
وبدون دفعة إحتياطية
Then there was the volcano
والامر الثاني .. البركان
that interrupted the travel plans
الذي اوقف حركة الملاحة الجوية
of almost all of you and many of your friends,
للكثير من اصدقائكم
including President Obama.
وحتى لرئيس دولتكم .. باراك حسين أوباما
By the way, the pronunciation
بالمناسبة .. ان لفظ البركان هو
is "Eyjafjallajokull."
( ايجافجالاجوكول )
None of your media got it right.
لا أحد من الاعلامين استطاع لفظ الاسم بصورة صحيحة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I'm not here to share these stories
ولكني لست هنا لكي اتشارك معكم القصص
about these two things exactly.
عن هذين الامرين
I'm here to tell you the story of Audur Capital,
انا هنا لكي اخبركم قصة شركة " آودور المالية "
which is a financial firm founded by me
وهي شركة مالية اسستها انا
and Kristin -- who you see in the picture --
وكرستين .. التي تظهر في الصورة هنا
in the spring of 2007,
في ربيع عام 2007
just over a year before the economic collapse hit.
اي قبل عام فحسب من صاعقة الازمة الاقتصادية
Why would two women
الآن لماذا تقوم
who were enjoying successful careers in investment banking
اثنتين من النسوة .. يملكن مهنة رائعة في مجال الاستثمار البنكي
in the corporate sector
في قطاع الشركات
leave to found a financial services firm?
بترك وظيفتهن .. وتأسيس شركة خدمات مالية ؟
Well let it suffice to say
دعوني أكتفي بالقول
that we felt a bit overwhelmed
اننا خدعنا بسبب الارتفاع
with testosterone.
في هرمون التستسترون لدينا !
And I'm not here to say
انا لست هنا لكي اقول
that men are to blame for the crisis
ان الرجال هم المسؤولون عن الازمة الاقتصادية
and what happened in my country.
وما حدث لدولتي
But I can surely tell you that in my country,
ولكن استطيع القول جازمةً
much like on Wall Street and the city of London and elsewhere,
ان في دولتي .. و في سوق وال ستريت .. او مدينة لندن .. او اي مكان آخر
men were at the helm
فإن الرجال هم على سدة الحكم
of the game of the financial sector,
فيما يتعلق في القطاع المالي
and that kind of lack of diversity
وهذا النقص الهائل في التنوع الجنسي
and sameness
والتشابه الهرموني
leads to disastrous problems.
هو الذي أدى الى هذه المشاكل الاضطرابية في النظام المالي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So we decided, a bit fed-up with this world
لذا قررنا .. ان نلهم العالم على نحو ما
and also with the strong feeling in our stomach
رغم ان " فراشات في معدتنا " كانت تجول
that this wasn't sustainable,
وتقول لنا انه من غير المستدام
to found a financial services firm
ان نؤسس شركة خدمات مالية
based on our values,
قائمة على قيمنا الانثوية
and we decided to incorporate feminine values
إذا قررنا ان ندمج القيم الانثوية
into the world of finance.
في العالم المالي
Raised quite a few eyebrows in Iceland.
كان الامر صعباً مثل انتظار نمو رموش الأعين
We weren't known
فنحن لم نكن معروفات
as the typical "women" women
نساء مثل النساء
in Iceland up until then.
في آيسلندا حتى ذلك الحين
So it was almost like coming out of the closet
ان الامر بدا كما لو اننا خرجنا من الخزانة
to actually talk about the fact that we were women
لكي نكشف السر ونقول اننا نسوة " ندير الشركة "
and that we believed that we had a set of values
واننا لدينا قناعات ... ولدينا قيم خاصة بنا
and a way of doing business
وطريقة للقيام بالاعمال
that would be more sustainable
والتي من وجهة نظرنا هي مستقرة
than what we had experienced until then.
اكثر من تلك التي تستخدم حتى ذلك الوقت
And we got a great group of people to join us --
وقد شاركنا مجموعة من الاشخاص الرائعين
principled people with great skills,
اشخاص أكفاء .. ذوي مهارات كبيرة
and investors with a vision
ومستثمرين ذوي رؤية بعيدة الامد
and values to match ours.
وقيم تشابه تلك التي لدينا
And together we got through the eye of the financial storm in Iceland
ومعاً استطعنا ان نمر عبر خندق الازمة المالية في آيسلندا
without taking any direct losses to our equity
دون ان نخسر اي شيء من اسهمنا
or to the funds of our clients.
او من حسابات عملائنا
And although I want to thank
ورغم اني اشكر
the talented people of our company
الاشخاص الموهوبين في شركنا
foremost for that --
لمعظم هذا العبور ..
and also there's a factor of luck and timing --
وايضا عامل الوقت والحظ ..
we are absolutely convinced
الا اننا مقتنعون تماما ..
that we did this because of our values.
اننا استطعنا ان نعبر هذا الخندق بسبب قيمنا
So let me share with you our values.
لذا دعوني اشارككم هذه القيم - قيمنا -
We believe in risk awareness.
نحن نؤمن بالوعي بالمخاطر
What does that mean?
ولكن ماذا يعني هذا ؟
We believe that you should always understand the risks that you're taking,
انه يعني اننا نؤمن انه يجب دوما أن نفهم المخاطر التي سنوشك على خوضها
and we will not invest
فنحن لا نستثمر
in things we don't understand.
في الامور التي لا نفهمها
Not a complicated thing.
انه ليس امرٌ معقد
But in 2007,
ولكن في 2007
at the height of the sub-prime
وعندما كان الرهن العقاري في ذروته
and all the complicated financial structures,
وكل تلك الانظمة الاقتصادية تزداد تعقيداً
it was quite opposite
رأينا نحن ان لا نستثمر على الاطلاق في السوق
to the reckless risk-taking behaviors
على عكس
that we saw on the market.
تصرفات بعض المستثمرين المتهورين
We also believe in straight-talking,
ونحن نؤمن بالكلام المباشر
telling it as it is,
" قل الامر كما هو "
using simple language that people understand,
واستخدم العبارات البسيطة التي يفهمها الناس
telling people about the downsides
واخبر الناس عن السلبيات
as well as the potential upsides,
وعن الايجابيات المتوقعة
and even telling the bad news that no one wants to utter,
وحتى اخبرهم عن الاخبار السيئة التي يرفض البعض الافصاح عنها
like our lack of belief in the sustainability
كوجهة نظرنا بعدم الاستقرار الاقتصادي
of the Icelandic financial sector
للقطاع المالي في آيسلندا
that already we had
والذي افادنا بامتناعنا عن الاستثمار فيه
months before the collapse hit us.
قبل عدة اشهر من عصف الازمة الاقتصادية بنا
And, although we do work in the financial sector,
ورغم اننا نعمل في القطاع المالي
where Excel is king,
حيث أن برنامج ميكروسوفت إكسل هو الملك
we believe in emotional capital.
فنحن نؤمن برأس المال العاطفي
And we believe
ونحن نؤمن
that doing emotional due diligence
ان الاعتناء بالناحية العاطفية
is just as important
هو مهم جداً
as doing financial due diligence.
كما الاعتناء بالناحية المالية
It is actually people
لان الناس في الحقيقة
that make money and lose money,
هي التي تدر الاموال .. او تخسر الاموال
not Excel spreadsheets.
لا صفحات ميكروسوفت اكسل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Last, but not least,
واخيراً وليس آخراً
we believe in profit with principles.
نحن نؤمن بالارباح ذات المبادىء
We care how we make our profit.
فنحن نهتم بالطريقة التي نستثمر فيها ومن اين تأتي ارباحنا
So while we want to make economic profit for ourselves and our customers,
فعندما نفكر باستثمار ما يدر علينا وعلى مستثمرينا أرباحاً ما
we are willing to do it with a long-term view,
فنحن نفكر برؤية بعيدة المدى
and we like to have a wider definition of profits
ونفضل ان نوسع تعريف أرباحنا
than just the economic profit in the next quarter.
اكبر من مجرد الارقام المالية التي تصدر كل ربع فصل
So we like to see profits,
لذا نحن نفضل ان نرى عوائد مالية
plus positive social
بالاضافة الى ايجابيات منعكسة على المجتمع ( جراء المشاريع التي نستثمر فيها )
and environmental benefits, when we invest.
وايضاً عوائد تلك المشاريع على البيئة
But it wasn't just about the values,
ولكن الامر ليس متعلقاً فحسب بتلك القيم
although we are convinced that they matter.
رغم اننا موقنون انها الاهم
It was also about a business opportunity.
انما الامر متعلق ايضاً بالفرص الاستثمارية
It's the female trend, and it's the sustainability trend,
انه منحى الاناث .. انه منحى مستدام
that are going to create
نحن سوف ننتج
some of the most interesting investment opportunities
فرصاً استثمارية مميزة جداً
in the years to come.
في الاعوام القادمة
The whole thing about the female trend
ان الامر كله متعلق بالمنحى الانثوي
is not about women being better than men;
انه ليس عبارة عن تحد لكي تصبح النساء افضل من الرجال
it is actually about
بل هو مجرد تذكير
women being different from men,
بان النساء هن مختلفات عن الرجال
bringing different values and different ways to the table.
بطرقهم المختلفة وبمناحيهم المختلفة وبمقاربتهم للحلول المختلفة
So what do you get? You get better decision-making,
إذا مالذي تحصل عليه من كل هذا ؟ انت تحصل على قدرة لاتخاذ القرار اكثر من ذي قبل
and you get less herd behavior,
وتحصل على استقلالية اكثر في التفكير
and both of those things hit your bottom line
وكل الامرين محورين جداً
with very positive results.
وينتجان نتائج ايجابية كبيرة
But one has to wonder,
ولكن على الفرد ان يتعجب من تلك النتائج
now that we've had this financial sector collapse upon us in Iceland --
لان انهيار القطاع المالي في آيسلندا قد اجتاح البلد بأكلمه
and by the way, Europe looks pretty bad right now,
وبالمناسبة ان اوروبا في خطر ايضا
and many would say that you in America
وانتم في امريكا ..
are heading for some more trouble as well.
ستواجهون بعض المتاعب ايضاً
Now that we've had all that happen,
وبما ان كل هذا قد حصل
and we have all this data out there
ونحن نملك المعلومات التي ادت لهذا
telling us that it's much better to have diversity
فان ذلك يجبرنا على ان نعتمد التمايز والاختلاف
around the decision-making tables,
في خصوص اتخاذ القرار الاسلم
will we see business and finance change?
والسؤال هو .. هل سنرى تغيراً اقتصاديا ؟
Will government change?
هل سوف تتغير الحكومة ؟
Well I'll give you my straight talk about this.
دعوني أكون صريحة معكم ..
I have days that I believe,
كنت اؤمن في بعض الايام ان هذا ممكن ..
but I have days that I'm full of doubt.
ولكن كانت تمر عدة ايام يخالجني الشك حيال هذا معظم الوقت ..
Have you seen the incredible urge out there
هل رأيتم الجدل الدائر هناك ..
to rebuild the very things that failed us?
في محاولة اعادة بناء النظام الذي خذلنا ؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Einstein said
لقد قال آينشتين
that this was the definition of insanity --
انه من الغباء
to do the same things
القيام بنفس الامر
over and over again,
مرة تلو الاخرى
hoping for a different outcome.
وان نتوقع انه يوماً ما سنحصل على نتيجة مغايرة
So I guess the world is insane,
لذا اظن ان العالم قد اصيب بالجنون ..
because I see entirely too much
لانه مصر بصورة كلية
of doing the same things over and over again,
على اعادة القيام بالامور بالطريقة القديمة ذاتها
hoping that this time it's not going to collapse upon us.
آملين فحسب ان لا ينهار الاقتصاد مرة أخرى فوق رؤوسنا
I want to see more revolutionary thinking,
انا ارغب برؤية تفكير ثوري أكثر
and I remain hopeful.
أريد أن ابقى متفائلة
Like TED, I believe in people.
مثل " مؤتمر تيد " .. انا اؤمن بمقدرة الافراد
And I know that consumers
وانا اعلم ان العملاء
are becoming more conscious,
اصبحوا اكثر ريبة
and they are going to start voting with their wallets,
وسيصبح تصويتهم السياسي معتمداً فحسب على المردود الاقتصادي
and they are going to change the face
وسوف يغيرون
of business and finance from the outside,
وجه الاقتصاد والاعمال من الخارج
if they don't do it from the inside.
ان لم نقم نحن به من الداخل
But I'm more of the revolutionary,
ولكن بالنسبة لي أفضل الفعل الثوري
and I should be; I'm from Iceland.
علي هذا .. فأنا من آيسلندا
We have a long history
ولدينا تاريخ طويل
of strong, courageous, independent women,
مليء بشخصيات نسائية مستقلة وقوية وشجاعة
ever since the Viking age.
منذ عصر الفايكنغ
And I want to tell you when
واريد ان اخبركم ايضاً
I first realized that women matter to the economy
انني ادركت أهمية المراة لاقتصاديات الدول
and to the society,
وللمجتمع
I was seven -- it happened to be my mother's birthday --
منذ كنت في السابعة من عمري .. لقد كان يومها عيد ميلاد والدتي
October 24, 1975.
24/اكتوبر/1975
Women in Iceland took the day off.
حيث حينها صدفت ان النسوة قررن التوقف يوماً كاملاً عن العمل
From work or from home, they took the day off,
سوء كان العمل داخل المنزل او خارجه .. لقد توقفوا تماماً
and nothing worked in Iceland.
فتوقفت آيسلندا تماما .. واصيبت بالشلل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They marched into the center of Reykjavik,
لقد سرن يومها الى مركز " ريكجافيك "
and they put women's issues onto the agenda.
ووضعوا قضايا المرأة حينها على طاولة الحوار
And some say this was the start of a global movement.
وقال البعض .. ان هذا التصرف حرك حركة عالمية من اجل حقوق المراة
For me it was the start of a long journey,
بالنسبة لي .. كانت بداية مسيرة طويلة
but I decided that day to matter.
منذ ذلك اليوم الذي قررت فيه ان اكون عضواً فاعلاً في المجتمع
Five years later,
بعد 5 سنوات منذ ذلك الحدث
Iceland elected Vigdis Finnbogadottir as their president --
انتخبت آيسلندا " فيجديس فينبوجادوتير " كرئيسة دولة
first female to become head of state,
كأول إمرأة تترأس البلاد
single mom,
والدة عزباء
a breast cancer survivor
وناجية من سرطان الثدي
who had had one of her breasts removed.
واجبرت على إستئصال أحد أثدائها تبعاً لذلك السرطان
And at one of the campaign sessions,
وقد عيرها يوم حملتها الانتخابية
she had one of her male contenders
احد المنافسين الذكور بقوله ..
allude to the fact that she couldn't become president --
انت لا يمكنك ان تصبحي رئيسة دولة
she was a woman, and even half a woman.
لانك إمرأة .. بل نصف إمرأة ..
That night she won the election,
في تلك الليلة فازت بالانتخابات
because she came back --
لانها ردت عليه
not just because of his crappy behavior --
وردت على ذلك التصرف المجحف
but she came back and said,
برد قوي حيث قالت
"Well, I'm actually not going to breastfeed the Icelandic nation;
أنا لست اترشح للانتخابات لكي " أُرضع آيسلندا "
I'm going to lead it."
انا أترشح من أجل قيادة البلد ! "
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I've had incredibly many
لدي الكثير من النسوة القدوة اللاتي ..
women role models
أثرن علي في حياتي
that have influenced who I am and where I am today.
وأوصلوني الى اما انا عليه اليوم
But in spite of that,
ورغم كل هذا
I went through the first 10 or 15 years of my career
قضيت فترة عملي الاولى بين 10-15 عاماً
mostly in denial of being a woman.
منكرة تماما كوني إمرأة
Started in corporate America,
فبدأت بشركة في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
and I was absolutely convinced
وكنت مقتنعة تماما ..
that it was just about the individual,
ان العمل ما هو الا نتاج فردي تام
that women and men would have just the same opportunities.
حيث يتوجب على المرأة والرجل الحصول على نفس العمل بنفس الفرص بنفس الشروط
But I've come to conclude lately
ومن ثم اكتشفت ان الامر
that it isn't like that.
ليس كذلك ..
We are not the same,
لاننا لسنا متشابهون .. ولا متساوون
and it's great. Because of our differences,
وهذا رائع .. لاننا مختلفون
we create and sustain life.
فحن نحافظ على استقرار واستمرارية الحياة بهذه الاختلافات
So we should embrace our difference and aim for challenge.
وعلينا ان نقدس هذه الاختلافات .. لانها تحد لنا جميعاً
The final thought I want to leave with you
واخر فكرة اريد ان اترككم معها
is that I'm fed up with this tyranny
هي انني قد ضقت ذرعاً
of either/or choices in life --
بالفكرة الطاغية التي تنص على قاعدة " إما / أو "
either it's men or it's women.
" اما الرجال / أو النساء "
We need to start embracing the beauty of balance.
علينا ان نبدأ بتقدير جمالية التوازن جراء الاختلاف
So let's move away
وعلينا ان نبتعد
from thinking about business here and philanthropy there,
عن فكرة الفصل بين الاعمال والمبادىء والهبات
and let's start thinking about
وعلينا ان نبدأ بالتفكير فحسب
doing good business.
بالقيام بالاعمال التجارية المفيدة
That's how we change the world. That's the only sustainable future.
وهذه هي الطريق الملائمة لتغير العالم .. وللحصول على مستقبل مستقر أكثر
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)